<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Densell Hollis esq., his speech at the delivery of the protestation to the Lords of the Upper House of Parliament, 4 May, 1641 wherein is set forth the reasons that moved the House of Commons to make the said protestation, together with a short narration of the severall grievances of the kingdome.</title>
            <author>Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2468A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43011</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11780001</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11780001</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49000</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49000)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1485:17 or 1720:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Densell Hollis esq., his speech at the delivery of the protestation to the Lords of the Upper House of Parliament, 4 May, 1641 wherein is set forth the reasons that moved the House of Commons to make the said protestation, together with a short narration of the severall grievances of the kingdome.</title>
                  <author>Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 1485:17 incorrectly identified as Wing H2473 variant, and at reel 1720:11 as Wing H2468A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49000:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:49000:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
            <p>
               <hi>DENSELL HOLLIS</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> HIS SPEECH At the delivery of the PROTESTATION TO the Lords of the upper Houſe of <hi>Parliament,</hi> 4. <hi>May,</hi> 1641. Wherein is ſet forth the reaſons that moved the houſe of Commons to make the ſaid PROTESTATION: <hi>Together with</hi> A Short Narration of the ſeverall grievances of the KINGDOME.</p>
            <p>London Printed, 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:49000:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <head>The Speech of Maſter <hi>Hollis</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Knights, and Burgeſſes, of the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, having taken into conſideration the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate and condition of this Kingdome, they finde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſurrounded with va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ety of pernitions and doſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory deſignes, practiſes and plots, againſt the wel-being of it, nay, the very being of it, and ſome of thoſe deſignes hatched within our owne bowels, and Viper-like work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>They finde Jeſuits and Prieſts conſpiring with ill Miniſters of State to deſtroy our religion, they finde ill Miniſters conjoyned together to ſubvertiour Lawes and liberties, they finde obſtructions of juſtice, which is the life and blood of every eſtate, and having free paſſage from the Sovereigne power, where it is primarily ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the life and blood in the heart, and thence deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved through the judicatories, on through ſo many veines into all the parts of this great Collective Body, doth give warmth and motion to every part and member which is: nouriſhed and enlivened by it, but being once precluded, ſtopped, and reared up, as the particular muſt needs faint, and languiſh, ſo muſt the whole frame of Government be diſlolved.</p>
            <p>And conſequently, Soveraignty it ſelfe which (as the heart in the body, is <hi>primum vivens, &amp; altimum moriens,</hi> muſt die and periſh in the generall diſſolution, and all things as in the beginning <hi>in antiquum Chaos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi> They finde the property of the ſubject in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded and violated, his eſtate rent from him by illegall taxations, Monopolies, and projects almoſt upon every thing that is for the uſe of man, not only upon ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities, but neceſſaries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that to enrich the Vermine and Caterpillers of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> impoveriſh good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to take the Meſſe from the Children, and give it to Dogs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords;</hi> If the Commons finde theſe things, they conceive they muſt needs bee ill Counſels that have brought us into this condition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49000:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <p>Theſe Counſels have put all into a combuſtion, have diſcouraged the hearts of all true Engliſh men, and brought two Armies into our bowels, which is the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon <hi>Prometheus,</hi> cates through, and ſucks and gnawes our very hearts out. <hi>Hic Dolor, ſed ub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Medicina?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heretofore Parliaments were the Catholicall, the balme of Gilead, which healed our wounds, reſtored our ſpirits, and made up the breaches of the Land.</p>
            <p>But of late yeares they have been like the fig-tree in the Goſpell, without efficacy, without fruit, only deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to their particular members, who diſcharged their duties and conſciences, no way beneſiciall to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. <hi>Nobis exitiale, nec Reipublicae profuturum,</hi> As he ſaid in <hi>Tacitus,</hi> being taken away ſtill as <hi>Elias</hi> was with a whirle-winde, never comming to any maturity, or to their naturall end, whereas they ſhould be like the bleſſed old man, who dyeth, <hi>plenus dierum,</hi> in a full age after he had fought a good ſight, and overcome all his enemies, or as the ſhock of wheat, which commeth in due ſeaſon to fill our Granaries with Corne, uphold our lives with the ſtaffe of bread, for Parliaments are our <hi>panis quotidianus,</hi> our true bread, all other waies are but <hi>Quelkachoes</hi> which yeeld no true nouriſhment, bread, nor good blood.</p>
            <p>The very Parliament which hath ſate ſo long, hath but beat the aire, and ſtrive againſt the ſtreame, I may truly ſay the winde and tide hath been ſtill againſt us. The ſame ill Counſell which firſt raiſed the ſtorme, and almoſt ſhipwrackt the Common-wealth, they ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, they blow ſtrong like the Eaſt winde that brought the Locuſts over our Counſels, croſſe our deſignes, caſt difficulties in our way, hinder our proceedings, and make all that we doe to be fruitleſſe and ineffectuall: They make us not maſters of our buſineſſe, and ſo not maſters of mony, which have been the great buſineſſe of this Parliament, that we might pay the Armies, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our promiſes and engagements.</p>
            <p>For my Lords, our not effecting of the good things
<pb facs="tcp:49000:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->which we had undertaken, for the good of the Church, and of the Common-wealth, hath wounded our reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and taken off from our credit.</p>
            <p>Is it not time then my Lords, that we ſhould unite and concentrate our ſelves, in regard of this <hi>Antiperiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> of hurtfull and malicious intentions and practices againſt us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi> it is moſt agreeable to nature, and I am ſure moſt agreeable to reaſon, in reſpect of the preſent conjuncture of our affaires, for one maine engine by which our enemies worke our miſchiefe, is by infuſing an opinion and beliefe into the world, that we are not united among our ſelves. But like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes, wee draw ſeverall waies, and tend to ſeverall ends.</p>
            <p>To defeat the Counſels of theſe <hi>Achitophels,</hi> which would involve us, Our Religion, our being, our Lawes, our liberties, and that can be neare and deare unto an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſoule, in one univerſall and generall deſolation, to defeat I ſay, the Counſels of evill <hi>Achitophels;</hi> the Knights, Citizens &amp; Burgeſſes of the houſe of commons (knowing themſelves to be ſpecially entruſted with the preſervation of the whole, and in their Conſcience are perſwaded that the dangers are ſo eminent, as they will admit of no delay) have thought fit to declare their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted affections by entring into an aſſociation amongſt themſelves, and by making a ſolemne proteſtation and vow unto their God, that they will unanimouſly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to oppoſe and prevent the Counſels and Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors which have brought upon us all theſe miſceries, and the feares of greater, to prevent the ends and bring the Authors of them to condigne puniſhment, and thereby diſcharge themſelves better before God and man.</p>
            <p>The Proteſtation your Lordſhips ſhall have read un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, together with the ground and reaſons which have induced the houſe of Commons to make it which are prefixed before it by way of Preamble. Then the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation was read by M. <hi>Maynard.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49000:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
